Boker Tov בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's daf דף daf is Lamed
Heh ל"ה Lamed Heh and we pick up at the very top
of Lamed Heh ל"ה. Lamed Heh. And the issue at stake here
is the Gemara's גמרא Gemara's question about whether if you have the
principle that Shabbos שבת Shabbos is koveia קובע koveia for ma'aser מעשר,
ma'aser, that Shabbos שבת Shabbos fruit that is
not yet—the halacha הלכה halacha is that if a fruit has not
had its gemar melacha גמר מלאכה gemar melacha finished, is in the
process of being finished, or even if it has the process of
being finished, has not yet been re'iyat pnei habayit ראיית פני הבית
re'iyat pnei habayit brought indoors, you can eat from it in a
temporary way, but just not in derech keva דרך קבע. derech keva.
You can snack from it, but you can't make a meal out
of it. But the halacha הלכה halacha is that on Shabbos שבת,
Shabbos, because of the importance of eating on Shabbos שבת, Shabbos, Shabbos
שבת Shabbos is koveia קובע, koveia, which means that it makes it
like it's not a snack, it makes it a permanent meal, and
you have to take terumot u'ma'asrot תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u'ma'asrot. And the
Gemara's גמרא Gemara's question is: Would that be true—we know it's true
about food that is done with the processing, it's nigmar melachto נגמר
מלאכתו, nigmar melachto, and just hasn't been brought in the house. Because
there you could say it's really only missing that one more
permanent context. But if the fruit itself is not yet finished in
the processing, you're not nigmar melachto נגמר מלאכתו, nigmar melachto, would Shabbos
שבת Shabbos have that impact or not? And so that's the question
at stake, whether Shabbos שבת Shabbos is koveia קובע koveia when it's
lo nigmar melachto לא נגמר מלאכתו. lo nigmar melachto. And the question
is about the issue here about the mishna משנה, mishna, because the
mishna משנה mishna talked about standing over the fruit on erev shevi'it
ערב שביעית erev shevi'it on erev shabbos ערב שבת erev shabbos on
shevi'it שביעית, shevi'it, where the implication would be that when Shabbos שבת
Shabbos would come along, if it was really obligated in
terumot u'ma'asrot תרומות ומעשרות, terumot u'ma'asrot,
then you'd be stuck. That sounds like Shabbos שבת Shabbos is koveia
קובע. koveia. But the Gemara גמרא Gemara managed to get out of
it. So now we pick up with this same question at the
top of Lamed Heh Amud Alef ל"ה עמוד א'. Lamed Heh Amud
Alef. Let's take a look.
Ve'halo והלא, Ve'halo, but is it not the case in this scenario
of the mishna משנה mishna of designating the fruit, where again it
sounds like in the mishna משנה mishna you would be stuck and
you would not be able to snack from it? And either that's
because Shabbos שבת Shabbos is koveia קובע, koveia, or the response the
Gemara גמרא Gemara had is maybe it's not that Shabbos שבת Shabbos
is koveia קובע, koveia, maybe it's that since you have to designate
in order to get out of muktza מוקצה muktza concerns, you have
to designate mikan ani ochel מכאן אני אוכל, mikan ani ochel, the
declaration "I am going to eat from this food" makes it into
keva קבע, keva, makes it into no longer snacking. So that's what
the Gemara's גמרא Gemara's going to challenge, if those words really would
be able to have that impact without the principle of Shabbos שבת
Shabbos koveia קובע. koveia. Ve'halo והלא, Ve'halo, says the Gemara גמרא, Gemara,
but would it not be the case that motaro chozer מותרו חוזר,
motaro chozer, that the remnant would go back? Because if you're saying
"I'm going to eat from this section", you'll eat what you eat,
but what you don't eat, you'll leave there. You won't even return
it, you don't even need to be returned, you'll just leave it
there. So big deal. Visham'inan lei l'Rabbi Eliezer ושמעינן ליה לרבי אליעזר,
Visham'inan lei l'Rabbi Eliezer, and we know that Rabbi Eliezer, who is
the person in the mishna משנה, mishna, the tanna תנא tanna in
the mishna משנה mishna that says that that's what you do is
you designate "I'm going to eat from here", d'amar דאמר, d'amar, kol
heicha d'motaro chozer כל היכא דמותרו חוזר, kol heicha d'motaro chozer, whenever
the remnant of the food that you're taking is going to go
back to where you took it from, lo kava לא קבע, lo
kava, it's not considered to be a permanent eating and you can
snack from it. D'tnan דתנן, D'tnan, let's see the case and then
we'll understand what he's talking about. We taught in the mishna משנה:
mishna: Hanotel zeitim min hama'atan הנוטל זיתים מן המעטן, Hanotel zeitim min
hama'atan, you take olives from the ma'atan מעטן, ma'atan, which is some
type of a vessel in which they're sitting and the gravity is
weighing them down and it's slowly causing the juices to start coming
out, and that's where you place them before you begin the pressing.
It makes the pressing of them easier. So you have
this vessel filled with olives, but they're olives that are not nigmar
melachtan נגמר מלאכתן, nigmar melachtan, they're in the process, you're waiting until
the next stage to then you're going to press them. Tovel achat
achat b'melach v'ochel טובל אחת אחת במלח ואוכל. Tovel achat achat b'melach
v'ochel. You can dip them individually in salt and eat them. That
obviously you don't have to dip them in salt, but that's the
way they would eat their olives. And that's an example of snacking.
So again, it's not nigmar melachto נגמר מלאכתו. nigmar melachto. You can
snack from them even if you haven't taken
terumot u'ma'asrot תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u'ma'asrot. Nigmar melachto נגמר מלאכתו Nigmar melachto
for zeitim זיתים? zeitim? Well, if they're things that you're going to
use in the process of making olive oil, it's only nigmar melachto
נגמר מלאכתו nigmar melachto when it's oil. That's why the Torah speaks
about taking terumot u'ma'asrot תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot from oil, right? It
says dagan tirosh v'yitzhar דגן תירוש ויצהר. dagan tirosh v'yitzhar.
But what if you were talking about olives that you might just
want to be eating?
No, that's why specifically they're in a ma'atan מעטן, ma'atan, because that's
part of the process of turning them into olive oil.
If you're planning on eating them,
that's a different story, but here they're clearly in the process of
becoming olive oil.
So that's what you can do. But v'im taval v'natan lefanav ואם
טבל ונתן לפניו—the v'im taval v'natan lefanav original mishna משנה mishna doesn't
have the word asara עשרה—meaning asara if you dipped a whole group
and you put in front of you, you took a whole plate
of them, then chayav חייב, chayav, then that's no longer snack. You
sat down with a plate of them, and there it's achilat keva
אכילת קבע achilat keva and you're chayav חייב. chayav. Rabbi Eliezer omer
רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, min hama'atan tahor chayav מן המעטן
טהור חייב—I'm min hama'atan tahor chayav sorry, min hama'atan tahor chayav מן
המעטן טהור חייב. min hama'atan tahor chayav. If you took them from
a
ma'atan מעטן ma'atan that was tahor טהור, tahor, and you take a
group to sit down and eat with, a pile of olives, then
you're obligated in terumot u'ma'asrot תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u'ma'asrot. Min hama'atan tamei
מן המעטן טמא. Min hama'atan tamei. If it's from an impure one,
פטור, patur, you're exempt, מפני שהוא מחזיר את המותר, mipnei shehu machzir
es hamutar, because you return what's left over. So what difference does
it make if it's טהור tahor or טמא? tamei? So it's pretty
obvious, but the גמרא Gemara spells it out. ואבינא בה, v'avinan bah,
we asked on this, מאי שנא רישא ומאי שנא סיפא, mai shna
reisha u'mai shna seifa, what difference does it make if the vessel
they were in was טהור tahor or טמא? tamei? ואמר רבי אבהו,
v'amar Rabbi Abbahu, רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu says, רישא במעטן טהור וגברא
טמא. reisha bema'atan tahor vegavra tamei. The first case, the problem is
that when you take them, you're going to make them טמא. tamei.
So the first case is they were all in a pure vessel,
all the olives were טהור, tahor, you were טמא. tamei. So what's
going to happen? You take them, you can't put the what's left
over back, you'll make all the rest of the olives טמא. tamei.
So in that case, דלא מצי מהדר ליה, d'lo matzi mahadar leh,
you can't return what's left over. So when you take a group
of olives to eat, that's it. They're taken away from their vessel
and they're not going to return because you've made them טמא. tamei.
But סיפא, seifa, in the second case, where the vessel is טמא,
tamei, במעטן טמא וגברא
טמא, bema'atan tamei vegavra tamei, it's טמא tamei and you're טמא, tamei,
דמצי מהדר ליה, dematzi mahadar leh, so you'll eat what you eat
and what you don't eat, you put back. And there's no problem
because so what they're טמא? tamei? They were טמא tamei to begin
with. Okay, fine. So that's just the difference. But what's the case?
What's the basic הלכה? halacha? והלכה vehalacha is you took a pile
of stuff, you sit down to eat from them. Is that קבע
keva or is that עראי? arai? That's the question, because if it's
before נגמרה מלאכתו, nigmara melachto, you can eat from them snacking, but
you can't sit down to a meal. So you've got this pile
of olives. Olives normally you don't consider to be קבע keva unless
you eat with bread or whatever. But okay, you took a whole
pile, you sat down, is that קבע? keva? So the תנא קמא
tanna kamma says yes. רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says if you're planning
on just eating what you need and putting the rest back, that's
not קבע, keva, that's עראי. arai. And therefore you do not, you
can do it that way even before taking תרומות ומעשרות. trumos uma'asros.
Okay, so that's what he says. So now how is that relevant
to us? Because us, we're saying that when you get up and
you say by these olives, by these food on the, in the
משנה Mishnah on שבת, Shabbos, on ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, on שביעית,
shvi'is, if
I'm going to eat from here tomorrow, we wanted to say that
that word of verbally designating makes the eating קבע. keva. So the
גמרא Gemara says, how can you say that makes the eating קבע?
keva? If when you actually took them, a pile of them, it's
not קבע keva since you're going to return the leftover. When you
only verbally designated, then the leftover is already returned. Anything you're not
going to eat is going to remain where it was. So it's
already in that back in that original state. How can that words
make it more קבע keva than the physically taking was on its
way back? Here it's not even on its way back, here it's
already back. So let's just read that. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
So the גמרא Gemara says, מתניתין
נמי,
matnisin nami,
במעטן טהור
וגברא טמא, bema'atan tahor vegavra tamei, דלא מצי מהדר ליה. delo matzi
mahadar leh. Okay. So our משנה, Mishnah, so the גמרא Gemara says,
wait a minute, we can get out of it! We can say
our משנה Mishnah is you're טמא tamei and the fruit or whatever
is טהור tahor and the whole sort of, you know, whatever,
the context is טהור, tahor, so therefore you won't be able to
put it back. So it's also a case of that you can't
return and it's also a case where it could be קבע. keva.
But it says no, בלאו מוחזרים ועומדים הם. belav muchzarim v'omdim heim.
What do you mean you can't put it back? They're already returned.
Meaning if you take, you're going to take from here and you
take five and you leave the rest behind, the rest remains טהור
tahor and you didn't even have to return them. They just remain
in their natural state. So the גמרא Gemara is saying if the
actual act of taking and sitting down to eat a pile of
them doesn't make it קבע keva because it's in a context where
the what's leftover will go back, so how could verbally designating making
it קבע keva if the whole reality is that anything you don't
eat is going to not only go back but is even going
to stay where it is? It all remains in the context of
that original location and anything eating is going to seem like a
mere type of a snack, not a real removing it from that
original context. So that is the גמרא's Gemara's again argument that it
can't just be that saying it does the job. It must be
a different principle. It must be the principle that being שבת Shabbos
is what makes it קבע. keva.
Yes, yes exactly that. So I don't understand the whole idea of
taking it back is not קבע. keva. So you're saying that like,
you know, let's say forget שבת, Shabbos, any meal. So if I
have this whole tray of chicken, so you know, I take it
out and then, you know, whatever, then I'm going to take...
no, so that's a very good question. Where, the question is where
are you taking it back to? If you're taking it back to
your kitchen or your refrigerator, it is קבע. keva. But here the
point is, thank you for clarifying, the point is you're taking it
back to that context in which it's not נגמרה מלאכתו, nigmara melachto,
in which it's still being processed. Right? So that's the issue. The
issue is is that if there, this thing is in the process,
I'm just like snacking a little bit. It's almost like the פסוקים
psukim in דברים, Devarim, right? When it's like, you know, when you're
going to, you know, work the grapes, you know, you can't stop
them from eating a few grapes. It's in the process, it's still,
this is not נגמרה מלאכתו. nigmara melachto. The fact that I'm eating
it doesn't mean it's done yet. The stuff is still in this
process. I'm just snacking a little bit. So if I'm taking, if
I take and I remove it and I bring it home and
I eat on my table, and what I'm not done with I
put in my refrigerator, this is out of that context of being
in the process of, you know, of finishing to its processing. It's
now in a completely different context. But if I take a handful,
I snack, and I put the rest back, then this is not,
this is still in that context
and
it's not. Yes, the
only question is maybe שבת Shabbos should.
Yes, you're טמא tamei and
the
מעטן, Ma'atan, yes, the מעטן Ma'atan is טהור. tahor. Right. So I
dip in to get some of the, right? So I can't put
those back because it's טמא. tamei. How come the whole thing doesn't
become טמא? tamei?
Okay, good question. So רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot ask that question
and the basic answer is one is maybe you scooped it out
with some type of a vessel that was not טמא tamei and
that you didn't make טמא tamei by handling it or you got
somebody to scoop it out for you. Or רש״י Rashi says even
if when you scooped it out you made the things you immediately
touched טמא, tamei, we can go ahead and we can like, you
know, remove from that section. But if you take a handful and
you throw it back, it'll get mixed up in everything else and
we won't know where they are. So that was, that's a good
question. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, but
that's the point and, you know, Michael's question was helpful in clarifying
that. What if they're still in the context of completing the processing,
even as you snack from them, then you're allowed to snack. Once
you've changed it and you've made it they're no longer in that
process, they're now part of your table and your meal and your
kitchen, then they're חייב. chayav. So the question is word shouldn't do
it if they, if they remain in that context, but maybe שבת
Shabbos does it, and that's the argument in our משנה, Mishnah, that
it is שבת Shabbos that should be doing it, not the word.
Okay, so now let's see as the גמרא Gemara continues. אלא אמר
רב שימי בר אשי, Ella amar Rav Shimi bar Ashi, so have
we not proven yet from our משנה Mishnah that it's שבת Shabbos
that has that impact? So רב שימי בר אשי Rav Shimi bar
Ashi says, רבי אליעזר קאמר לה, Rebbe Eliezer ka'amar lah, one minute,
our משנה's Mishnah רבי אליעזר, Rebbe Eliezer, right? He's the one who
said you get up and you say I'm going to eat from
this, etc., and therefore the implication being that if it weren't שביעית,
Shvi'is, it would be a problem to eat from it. So that's
רבי אליעזר. Rebbe Eliezer. רבי אליעזר לטעמיה, Rebbe Eliezer letamei, רבי אליעזר
Rebbe Eliezer goes according to his reasoning, you're right, our משנה Mishnah
assumes that it would be אכילת קבע achilat keva because presumably because
of שבת. Shabbos. But that's because we're working within the position of
רבי אליעזר, Rebbe Eliezer, and רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer in general is
more ready to see things that makes things considered אכילת קבע achilat
keva and obligated in תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u'ma'asrot. דאמר, De'amar, because רבי
אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer goes according to his reasoning who says תרומה קבעה,
teruma kav'a, that the taking of תרומה teruma makes it what's left
into אכילת קבע. achilat keva. וכל שכן שבת, Ve'chol sheken Shabbat, and
certainly something like שבת. Shabbos. I kept, I don't exactly understand the
כל שכן, kol sheken, but anyway, let's see the position of רבי
אליעזר. Rebbe Eliezer. דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the משנה Mishnah in
מעשרות, Ma'asrot, פירות
שתרמן עד שלא נגמר מלאכתן. perot she'traman ad shelo nigmar melachtan. So
let's say you have this fruit up on the roof drying out
or these olives waiting to be pressed, and you decided, so it's
a funny הלכה, halacha, on the one hand you can eat from
it עראי, arai, right? Not קבע, keva, as long as it's not
נגמר מלאכתו. nigmar melachto. When it's נגמר מלאכתו nigmar melachto it is
completely obligated in תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot and eating from it even
a bit you'll be חייב chayav in eating טבל. tevel. Before it's
נגמר מלאכתו, nigmar melachto, it's not, it's not yet absolutely obligated. But
what I mean it's not absolutely obligated, it has the potential of
taking תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot from it. You can choose to take
תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot from it before נגמר מלאכתו. nigmar melachto. You
might even remember an earlier discussion in the גמרא Gemara that had
the לוי Levi coming to you in the field after you've just
cut down the wheat and you're giving it to him as מעשר
ma'aser before you've even given the תרומה. teruma. So even before נגמר
מלאכתו nigmar melachto you can choose, you can take תרומות ומעשרות terumot
u'ma'asrot and it'll be good, but it doesn't become absolutely obligated in
the point that's considered eating טבל tevel until נגמר מלאכתו. nigmar melachto.
So let's say you went ahead and you had this fruit drying
out on your roof or you had these olives waiting to be
pressed, where we say you're allowed to snack from it, and you
said you know what, I'm not going to wait for them to
be pressed or dried out, I'm just going to take תרומה teruma
right now. תרומה's Teruma easy, it can be a tiny amount. Okay,
so you take your תרומה, teruma, but I'll wait to take מעשר
ma'aser and do the whole weighing and getting exactly ten percent, that
I'll wait till I'm done. Does the fact that you've taken תרומה
teruma and now you've created, you know, what you took into תרומה,
teruma, does that turn everything else into considering like okay, now it's
sort of done, you know, from the perspective of תרומות ומעשרות terumot
u'ma'asrot once you've started taking it, the rest is locked in already,
it's considered fully טבל tevel and now you can't even eat from
it in a temporary way? And that's what רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer
says. He says דתנן, detnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, פירות
שתרמן עד שלא נגמר מלאכתן, perot she'traman ad shelo nigmar melachtan, so
you took תרומה teruma before they finished being processed. רבי אליעזר אוסר
לאכול מהם עראי, Rebbe Eliezer oser le'echol mehem arai, says once you've
taken תרומה, teruma, that's it, now the rest is totally טבל, tevel,
you can't even snack from it. וחכמים מתירין, Ve'chachamim matirin, and the
חכמים Chachamim allow. So what we are saying is that this is
interesting because obviously they're not נגמר מלאכתן, nigmar melachtan, it's not objectively
true about them, but they've entered into some halachic state according to
רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer where it changes their status, or changes the
nature of the idea of what eating from them means. So if
that's true by תרומה, teruma, it would certainly be true by שבת,
Shabbos, because as we said שבת Shabbos makes the eating important. So
fine, yes, our משנה Mishnah assumes that there'd be a problem that
if it weren't שביעית, Shvi'is, there'd be a problem eating from this.
Why? Why can't you snack? Yes, it's true, because שבת Shabbos makes
it קבע keva even though it's not finished in the processing. But
that's רבי אליעזר. Rebbe Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer even says that
תרומה teruma makes it קבע. keva. This different halachic reality changes it
even though it is not finished in the processing. That's the, that's
true, but you haven't proven your position according to the חכמים. Chachamim.
So now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says.
Let's look at the end, but the end only the first half
of that משנה Mishnah is רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. The end of
the משנה Mishnah is the חכמים. Chachamim. So the גמרא Gemara says,
תא שמע מסיפא, Ta shma misseifa, let's look at the end of
the משנה, Mishnah, our משנה. Mishnah. והחכמים אומרים עד שיאמר מכאן ועד
כאן, Vehachachamim omrim ad sheyomar mikan ve'ad kan,
I'm going to eat from here to here. So look, the חכמים,
Chachamim, the whole debate in the משנה Mishnah between רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer and the חכמים Chachamim is what do you need to get
out of מוקצה? muktzah? But everybody implicitly agrees that the reason you're
allowed to eat from this food is because it's שביעית. Shvi'is. And
if it wasn't שביעית, Shvi'is, you wouldn't be allowed to eat from
it. So we go back to our question: why not? Why would
you not be allowed to snack from it? Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, טעמא, taima, so this is the חכמים Chachamim that don't
buy into רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, don't buy into this idea that
תרומה trumah makes it קבע. keva. And nevertheless, we see, טעמא דערב
שבת ושביעית, taima d'erev Shabbos v'Shvi'is, the reason that it's only a
מוקצה muktzah issue
is because שמיטה, Shmitah, דלאו בר איסורי נינהו, d'lav bar issurei ninhu,
you don't take תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros on שמיטה. Shmitah. הא בשאר
שני שבוע, ha b'sh'ar shenei shavua, if it was the rest of
the years of the cycle, דבני איסורי נינהו, d'vnei issurei ninhu, that
they're obligated in מעשר, maaser, אסורי. assuri. So both רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer and the חכמים Chachamim agree you could not eat from the
food if it wasn't שמיטה. Shmitah. Their only debate is how to
address the מוקצה muktzah issue. So we're back to the question: why
can't you eat from it, why can't you just snack from it?
Okay, it must be because it's שבת. Shabbos. And those have, oh
no, it's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who is more ready to see
things as קבע. keva. This is the חכמים. Chachamim. Okay, so מאי
טעמא, mai taima, why is it? לאו משום דשבת קבע, lav mishum
d'Shabbos kava, isn't it because שבת Shabbos is קובע? koveya? So the
גמרא Gemara says, לא, lo, no, same thing it said yesterday for
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. שאני התם, shani hasam, כיון דאמר מכאן ועד
כאן אני אוכל למחר, keivan d'amar mikan ve'ad kan ani ochel lemachar,
since you have to say, I'm going to eat from here to
here, you specifically designate this is the food I'm going to eat,
so קבע ליה, kava leh, that designation is what makes it קבע,
keva, not the fact that it's שבת. Shabbos. But it's the sort
of catch-22, you've got to designate it to get it out of
מוקצה, muktzah, and that act of designating it actually makes it that
it's אכילת קבע. achilas keva. Now the גמרא Gemara challenged it earlier
for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer because it said that's not different than
רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer's principle that if you return the leftover, right,
that it remains
עראי. arai. But here, it doesn't have that challenge, since this is
the חכמים. Chachamim. Right, it was only רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that
says if you return the leftover it remains עראי. arai. This is
the חכמים, Chachamim, so this answer now works for the חכמים. Chachamim.
Okay, well let's read it. So the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי,
ei hachi, מאי איריא שבת, mai irya Shabbos, אפילו בחול נמי? afilu
bechol nami? If that's true, why are we talking about שבת? Shabbos?
We should be talking about a weekday. Which is again, a funny
question, but meaning if that's
the חידוש chiddush to tell you that by designating you make it
into אכילת קבע, achilas keva, then they shouldn't have given me an
example by שבת, Shabbos, they should have just told me in general
by תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros designating it makes it אכילת קבע. achilas
keva. Why do you give me this complicated case by שבת? Shabbos?
Why did you sort of intersect this with a מוקצה muktzah discussion?
So the גמרא Gemara says, no, הא קמשמע לן, ha kamashma lan,
it's teaching me the same thing it said yesterday, דטבל מוכן הוא
אצל שבת, detvel muchan hu eitzel Shabbos,
that even though something is טבל tevel and you're rabbinically forbidden to
take תרומות ומעשרות, trumos u'maasros, but nevertheless, it would still not be
מוקצה muktzah if again, let's say it's נגמר מלאכתו. nigmar melachto. If
the problem here in the משנה Mishnah was that the fruit was
still drying out. But let's say the fruit was completely done and
ready to be eaten, you had these nice, wonderful, juicy apples, but
the problem was, was that it hadn't taken תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros
taken from it, so you can't eat on שבת Shabbos because it's
אסור, assur, because it's טבל. tevel. But דאם עבר ותיקנו מתוקן, de'im
avar v'tikno metukan, if בדיעבד bedieved was somebody went and violated and
took תרומות ומעשרות, trumos u'maasros, it wouldn't be מוקצה. muktzah. Again, a
very bizarre הלכה. halacha. Right, שבת Shabbos began, it was טבל, tevel,
it was completely אסור. assur. But now they're saying is that בדיעבד
bedieved if somebody went ahead on שבת Shabbos and took תרומות ומעשרות,
trumos u'maasros, it does not have a status of מוקצה. muktzah. Since
when שבת Shabbos began, even though it was אסור, assur, the only
prohibition was a rabbinic prohibition that does not make it considered completely
off limits. Again, very strange. Normally we would say that if something
was off limits, what do I care if biblical or rabbinic? שבת
Shabbos began, it was off limits. Again, maybe this is a little
bit different because it's food, and food is considered to be so
much out of the מוקצה muktzah category, so much the basic thing
that you are going to benefit from and eat from that you
need it to be more objectively or more, you know, with greater
barriers pushed away. So if this is a very interesting הלכה halacha
that if somebody בדיעבד bedieved went ahead and fixed and your תרומות
ומעשרות, trumos u'maasros, it would not be מוקצה, muktzah, and the only
reason in the משנה Mishnah there's a מוקצה muktzah issue is not
because it's טבל, tevel, but because it is up drying on the
roof and that's what makes it מוקצה, muktzah, not its טבל. tevel.
So how do we read that from the משנה? Mishnah? Again to
repeat what we said yesterday, because since the משנה Mishnah says that
what you do is ערב שבת erev Shabbos you get up and
if it's שמיטה Shmitah then you don't have to worry about תרומות
ומעשרות, trumos u'maasros, you designate this and this and this I'm going
to eat. So the point is, is that the implication is that
you're allowed to do לכתחילה lechatchila if it were שמיטה. Shmitah. If
it weren't שמיטה, Shmitah, you would not be allowed to designate I'm
going to eat from here, because it's a problem, it's טבל tevel
and you're not allowed to, but בדיעבד, bedieved, the משנה Mishnah is
only talking about לכתחילה, lechatchila, בדיעבד bedieved if it went ahead and
somebody actually went ahead. If it fixed actually it would not be
a מוקצה Muktzah problem. Now so this is a very again radical
idea that טבל Tevel would not be מוקצה Muktzah if it got
fixed and the גמרא Gemara is introducing it to answer like a
difficult question in the משנה Mishnah just again clarify because it's not
so clear what's going on in here. The point is the משנה
Mishnah says this food because it's שמיטה Shmita can be eaten on
שבת Shabbos if you fix the מוקצה Muktzah problem. So the גמרא's
Gemara question is why couldn't it be eaten on שבת Shabbos anyway
even if it weren't שמיטה Shmita because it's only going to be
if it'll only be a temporary eating? So doesn't this prove that
שבת Shabbos is קובע? koveia? The question and the answer is no,
maybe there's a different reason, maybe it's because you verbally designated it
that's why etc. And then the גמרא Gemara says okay but the
interesting thing that's going on in this משנה Mishnah is the idea
that the verbal designation changes its status and doesn't allow you to
be temporary. Why do we give this very that's the חידוש chidush
it's a חידוש chidush to be taught over in מעשרות. Ma'asros. Why
are we giving this example in the context of שבת Shabbos יום
טוב Yom Tov and מוקצה Muktzah and so on? And it says
that's to tell you another another הלכה halacha it's to tell you
the הלכה halacha that all of this is only לכתחילה lechatchila implicitly
in the way the משנה Mishnah is phrased but בדיעבד bedi'avad if
you know even though we're dealing with real טבל Tevel בדיעבד bedi'avad
that won't be מוקצה. Muktzah. And the only problem here is because
it's up on the roof drying out and that's why it's מוקצה
Muktzah the טבל Tevel aspect is not really what makes it מוקצה.
Muktzah. Alright so again a little complicated but that's where we are.
Dov you had a question before?
Yeah two things one is first of all to me it makes
a lot of strong sense that the verbalization would transform the eating
to קבע keva because you don't do that when you snack. Right.
You don't pre-plan. Right. So that's
like I feel very clear point. The second thing is I don't
know why the גמרא Gemara felt compelled to make this חידוש chidush
about טבל Tevel because I would understand contextualizing this in שבת Shabbat
because that's when you would be apt to make such a verbalization.
Yeah I agree with you I agree the fact that the גמרא
Gemara feels like here why says oh teach it to me in
a weekday scenario and it has to say this. I mean there's
a big רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosfos that try to explain why
the גמרא Gemara feels that's the question. I mean it's obvious like
you said A that's where you would make the verbalization B we
want to teach it here because it's an interesting case in terms
of a מוקצה Muktzah question. You know it's like the גמרא Gemara
is saying well now that we've decided that the real חידוש chidush
here is about the דיבור dibbur why are we teaching about it
here and not over there? Yeah I agree so it's hard to
see what compelled the גמרא Gemara to come up with another חידוש
chidush of the משנה Mishnah and the חידוש chidush itself is pretty
radical is not something we normally say. If normally something is off
limits it remains off limits what do I care it's a דרבנן?
DeRabbanan? So it is hard what compelled the גמרא Gemara to say
it and it's a big חידוש chidush what the גמרא Gemara does
say. Okay. That in a way that in a way is more
of what emerges
from... anyway that for us I would say is more of a
practical חידוש chidush this טבל Tevel idea and practical anyway the idea
that something that you know the concept behind it... then this issue
here about the גמר מלאכה g'mar melacha and שבת Shabbos קובע koveia
which is sort of certain less relevant to our הלכתי halachic universe.
Okay but anyway the גמרא Gemara has now said in the משנה
Mishnah why can't you snack from it? Either yes שבת Shabbos is
קובע koveia but that's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who's willing to say
other things are קובע koveia like תרומה Terumah is קובע koveia taking
out תרומה Terumah or the חכמים Chachamim but then it's not שבת
Shabbos is קובע koveia then it's just the דיבור dibbur is קובע
koveia and that's what's going on since you said מכאן עד כאן
mikan ad kan you're caught in this catch-22. And for the חכמים
Chachamim you can't say how is it any different than the idea
of putting the rest back where it's not קובע koveia that was
a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer idea. The חכמים Chachamim say I don't
care if you're going to put the rest back so even though
here it's all already put back doesn't matter. So either it's the
דיבור dibbur is קובע koveia or it's שבת Shabbos is קובע koveia
those are the two reads of our משנה. Mishnah. Let's get a
little bit further okay because it's a little confusing I want to
sort of get a little more context go a little further. So
גמרא Gemara says like this: רמי. Ramei.
So now we're sort of done saying that we understand you can
ask the משנה Mishnah in different ways but now we're going to
have a problem of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer seeming to contradict himself.
Okay let's ask we have another משנה Mishnah in תרומות. Terumos. היה
אוכל באשכול Haya ochel be'eshkol you're eating from a cluster of grapes.
It's assumed to be that the cluster of grapes is not נגמר
מלאכתו nigmar melachto because basically what do you do with olives you
turn them to olive oil what do you do with grapes you
turn them into wine.
So there you are you're snacking on a cluster of grapes. היה
אוכל ונכנס מגינה לחצר Haya ochel venichnas migina l'chatzer and you went
from your garden into the חצר. chatzer. Now the חצר chatzer is
like the בית bayis like we talked before and if it were
נגמר מלאכתו nigmar melachto the bringing of it into the חצר chatzer
makes it is קובע koveia but here it's not נגמר מלאכתו nigmar
melachto it's still grapes it's not yet wine. So רבי אליעזר אומר
יגמור Rabbi Eliezer omer yigmor go ahead and finish your snacking רבי
יהושע אומר לא יגמור Rabbi Yehoshua omer lo yigmor don't finish your
snacking because it had coming into a חצר chatzer so even though
it's not נגמר מלאכתו nigmar melachto which is strange because we said
before not נגמר מלאכתו nigmar melachto and a חצר chatzer is okay.
But okay we'll see about that. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says finish
your snacking. Now here becomes the more relevant problem: חשכה בלילי שבת
chashcha beleilei Shabbat you were snacking on these grapes on Friday and
then it became dark and it became שבת. Shabbos. So here is
the idea of
שבת. Shabbos. So here it seems to be, it's so funny, we
went to all of these convolutions whether שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* is קובע
koveia *koveia*. This seems to now be exactly what רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer *Rebbi Eliezer* and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rebbi Yehoshua* are arguing
about. You're eating your grapes, it's not נגמר מלאכתו nigmar melachto, *nigmar
melachto*, becomes שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua, *Rebbi Yehoshua* says
keep on eating. I mean, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rebbi Eliezer* says
keep on eating. שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* isn't קובע koveia. *koveia*. רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua *Rebbi Yehoshua* says don't keep on eating. שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*
is קובע koveia *koveia*. Here it's exactly what's being debated. So for
whatever reason the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* did not bring this in, maybe
then we would have all lost all the fun of trying to
fit it into our משנה Mishnah *mishnah*, I don't know, but okay.
But what we now have is a problem of רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer *Rebbi Eliezer* on himself. Because we just got through saying that
the משנה Mishnah *mishnah*, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rebbi Eliezer*'s position in
the משנה Mishnah *mishnah* that these things are a problem if it
weren't שמיטה *shemitah* is because שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* is קובע koveia, *koveia*.
And here he says in this case finish eating the grapes, שבת
Shabbos *Shabbat* isn't קובע koveia, *koveia*. So how do you make sense
of this? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says התם כדקתני טעמא
*hatam kideka tani taama*. No, no, no. You have to understand what's
going on in that משנה Mishnah: *mishnah*. Here's we explain the reason.
רבי נתן *Rebbi Natan* אומר *omeir*, רבי נתן *Rebbi Natan* says לא
כשאמר רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer יגמור בחצר יגמור *lo keshe'amar Rebbi Eliezer
yigmor bechatzer yigmor*. When רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. *Rebbi Eliezer* says finish
and you're in the חצר chatzer, *chatzer*, he doesn't literally mean finish.
Okay, what does he mean? אלא *ella*, he doesn't mean finish eating
while you're in the חצר chatzer *chatzer*. יוציא חוץ לחצר ויגמור *yotzi
chutz lachatzer veyigmor*. Take it out of the חצר chatzer, *chatzer* and
finish eating. Being in the חצר courtyard. *chatzer* does not turn it
into a,
you know, that you can't eat from it without taking תרומות ומעשרות
Terumos uMaaseros *terumot umaasrot*. But what it does mean is while you're
in the חצר courtyard *chatzer*, you can't eat from it. That would
be considered אכילת קבע keva, *achilat keva*. Take it back out and
you'll be fine. ולא כשאמר רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer יגמור בשבת יגמור
*velo keshe'amar Rebbi Eliezer yigmor beShabbat yigmor*. When he says you can
finish it, it doesn't mean finish eating it on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat*.
אלא *ella*, what he means is ממתין למוצאי שבת Shabbos ויגמור *mamtin
lemotzaei Shabbat veyigmor*. Just because it became שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat* is not
going to create a problem after שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*. Wait till מוצאי
שבת Shabbos *motzaei Shabbat* ויגמור *veyigmor* and finish it. Okay, doesn't sound
like what he's saying. But what is he saying now? So it's
interesting, when we say שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* is קובע koveia, *koveia*, it
could mean one of two things. It could mean it changes the
status once שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat* passes over, the status of the grapes
is changed or the food is changed and now even after שבת
Shabbos *Shabbat* you can't snack from it. Now it's considered like it's
done. Okay, and that's one possibility. The other possibility, doesn't, not so
clear why that should be true. Remember the reason we said שבת
Shabbos *Shabbat* is קובע koveia *koveia* is וקראת לשבת עונג *vekarata leShabbat
oneg*. That eating on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* is considered like serious, weighty,
important eating. So if that's true, it doesn't change the status of
the grapes. What it means is that when you eat on שבת
Shabbos, *Shabbat*, that type of an eating is not considered snacking. But
if it went through שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* and you're eating it on
Sunday, the status of the grapes remains the same. Now רש״י *Rashi*
does say, because there was a משנה Mishnah, *mishnah* we quoted at
the beginning of the סוגיא sugya *sugya*, that if you remember the
kids hiding the figs in the field for שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, that
maybe if you were to put the grapes aside and say I'm
going to eat these on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, that then changes their
identity even on Sunday. But if you haven't designated it for שבת
Shabbos *Shabbat*, it just happens to be שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, then the
only problem is their status hasn't changed for Sunday, the problem is
don't eat it today, the eating today will not be considered snacking.
So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rebbi Eliezer* says that in this case
here, is it a גמר מלאכה gmar melachah, *gmar melachah* or not
a גמר מלאכה gmar melacha. *gmar melachah*? I mean, what's the status
of שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* when it's not נגמר מלאכתו nigmar melachto, *nigmar
melachto*? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, *Rebbi Eliezer* says you can finish. But
he doesn't mean you can eat it now on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*.
Eating on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* is considered אכילת קבע keva. *achilat keva*.
What he means is you can hold it till after שבת Shabbos.
*Shabbat* and eat it after שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat*. That's what he would
say. So how does this resolve רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, *Rebbi Eliezer*?
Again, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, *Rebbi Eliezer* in the משנה mishnah *mishnah*
says we're talking about שמיטה *shemitah*, this stuff that's drying out on
your roof. If it weren't שמיטה *shemitah*, the implication would be you
can't snack from it. Why not? Not נגמר מלאכתו *nigmar melachto*. Must
be that at least רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, *Rebbi Eliezer* holds שבת
Shabbos *Shabbat* is קובע koveia. *koveia*. Okay, but now we've clarified what
does that mean שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* is קובע koveia. *koveia*. It means
snacking, if the snacking is on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, then it's considered
a fixed meal and you have to take תרומות ומעשרות Terumos uMaaseros
*terumot umaasrot*. Here where he says finish eating your grapes, he says
you can wait till after שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat* and finish it. That's
fine. But if you wanted to eat it on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat*,
then even רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rebbi Eliezer* would say, and that's
the assumption in the משנה mishnah? *mishnah*, that שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat* is
קובע koveia, *koveia*.
If I had a plate of figs on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat*, I
should בענטש *bench* after I'm done.
I'm not sure קביעה *keviah* is exactly the same as בענטשן *benching*,
but okay.
Now, now I do want to say that now what's so funny
again, because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* went through all of this complicated
discussion of is שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* קובע koveia, *koveia* based on our
משנה mishnah *mishnah*. But now what have we found out? That both
רבי אליעזר *Rebbi Eliezer* and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rebbi Yehoshua* say
that שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat* is קובע koveia, *koveia*. Right, they both agree
that you cannot eat it on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat* itself. The whole
debate we've now said is can you even finish the grapes after
שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat*. Right, there רבי אליעזר *Rebbi Eliezer* says once it's
Sunday then you can eat them. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rebbi Yehoshua*
says no, you can't eat them even on Sunday. But they both
agree you can't eat them on שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*, right? So they
both say that שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* is קובע koveia, *koveia*, sort of,
you know, and it's so funny that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sort
of, you know, did these acrobatics to try to figure it out.
Here both of them seem to agree the way we've framed
it that שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat* is קובע koveia. *koveia*. The גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay,
so where are we? So, okay, we had a whole complicated issue
whether our משנה mishnah assumes that שבת is קובע koveia. because our
משנה mishnah. assumes you can't snack. We basically said maybe רבי אליעזר
holds it but the חכמים Chachamim don't necessarily hold it. Now we've
seen that both רבי אליעזר and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua, say that
on שבת itself it would be a problem. Everybody there seems to
say שבת is קובע. koveia. The whole debate is after שבת whether
you can eat and there רבי אליעזר is more lenient and says
after שבת then you can go back to eating from it. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: כי אתא רבין אמר רבי יוחנן אחד שבת ואחד תרומה ואחד
חצר ואחד מקח כולם אין קובעין אלא בדבר שנגמרה מלאכתן. Ki aso
Ravin amar Rabbi Yochanan echad Shabbat ve'echad trumah ve'echad chatzer ve'echad mekach
kulam ein kovin ela bedavar shenigmerah melachtan. So although all of this
evidence until now has been pushing in the direction that שבת is
קובע koveia even when it's finished process- before it's finished processing, the
statement now from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael in the name of רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is against it. Whether שבת, whether תרומה, trumah, we
saw before the idea that תרומה trumah was קובע, koveia the tasting
of תרומה, trumah, whether being in the חצר, yard that was also
the debate between רבי אליעזר and רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, right? If
it's in the חצר courtyard while you're eating your cluster of grapes,
whether it's a sale, a purchase, maybe that gives it weight and
makes it sort of changes its identity. None of those makes it
קבע, keva. makes it a problem, makes eating from it a problem
if you're snacking from it, unless it's finished in the processing, אלא
שנגמרה מלאכתן. ela shenigmerah melachtan. But before גמר מלאכה, gemar melacha, all
of these are not a problem, so everything we said before would
not be, you know, all the ways we read our משנה Mishna
and we read רבי אליעזר and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua, that שבת
is קובע, koveia that's not להלכה. lehalachah. Okay, let's now go through
this list.
So שבת, the שבת is not
קובע, koveia ולאפוקי מדהלל, ve'apukei mideHillel, to exclude the position of הלל.
Hillel. Again, funny, could have said to exclude רבי אליעזר. We've just
been talking about שבת being קובע koveia for the last דף. daf.
Now we're going to be introduced to yet another position that שבת
is קובע. koveia. דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא: Baraisa: המעמר
פירות ממקום למקום לקצור. Hame'amer peiros mimakom lemakom liktzor. Now that's a
very strange phrase. You're piling up the fruit, המעמר's me'amer like gathering
them up in a big pile in the yard, from place to
place in order to harvest them. What does that mean? So, the
other, the better גרסא girsa is המעביר פירות ממקום למקום, hama'avir peiros
mimakom lemakom, not your המעמר me'amer but your המעביר, ma'avir, you're transporting
them, and not לקצור liktzor but לקצץ, lekatzetz, in order to, remember
that's the verb we've been using until now, the מוקצה. muktzah. You're
transporting them and you're going to dry them out. So it's not
נגמרה מלאכתן. nigmerah melachtan. Okay, וקידש עליהם היום, vekidesh aleihem hayom, and
now it's שבת. A perfect another example of שבת in something that's
not נגמרה מלאכתן. nigmerah melachto. אמר רבי יהודה, Amar Rabbi Yehuda, says
רבי יהודה: Rabbi Yehuda: הלל לעצמו אוסר. Hillel le'atzmo oser. הלל Hillel
was the only one who said that was a problem. So again,
quite bizarre. We've been doing acrobatics to figure out is שבת קובע.
koveia. We just got through seeing at the very end of the
סוגיא sugya, quotes a ברייתא Baraisa of רבי אליעזר and רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua that they, that at least רבי יהושע says שבת is
קובע, koveia in the way the גמרא Gemara. interprets it רבי אליעזר
as well, you're eating the cluster of grapes, it's שבת, it's a
problem. Now we see a ברייתא Baraisa that says הלל Hillel says
שבת is קובע, koveia right, that שבת once it became שבת you
can't eat from it. Okay, so again all of this evidence that
שבת being קובע, koveia. it's funny that it comes at the end
of the סוגיא, sugya. but now we're saying הלל לעצמו. Hillel le'atzmo.
הלל Hillel was the only one. Of course we had רבי אליעזר,
רבי יהושע, we had those other things. Okay, what?
Yeah, he said it for himself alone.
No,
he alone, he alone was the one who said it was a
problem. Okay, so on the one hand we've seen now more explicit
evidence that שבת is קובע, koveia רבי אליעזר, רבי יהושע, הלל. Hillel.
On the other hand we're trying- we're marginalizing it. We're saying it
was only really הלל Hillel and therefore we don't פוסקן pasken that
way. Okay, so שבת is not קובע. koveia. חצר, courtyard now the
top of ל"ה עמוד ב', lamed-hei amud-beis, a
חצר. chatzer. ולאפוקי מדרבי יעקב. le'apukei mideRabbi Yaakov. So even being in
the חצר chatzer if it's not done processing is not a problem,
then that is to reject the position of רבי יעקב. Rabbi Yaakov.
דתנן, detnan, we taught in a משנה: Mishna, המעביר תאנים בחצרו לקצץ.
Hama'avir te'einim bechatzeiro lekatzetz. Again, that's המעביר לקצץ, ma'avir lekatzetz, that same
combination. You're transporting figs in your חצר chatzer and to dry them
out. So again, these are not נגמרה מלאכתן, nigmerah melachtan, these are
figs. בניו ובני ביתו אוכלין מהם עראי ופטורין מן המעשר. Banav uvnei
beiso ochlin mehem arai ufturin min hama'aser. That's what we taught at
the beginning of the סוגיא. sugya You know, people in your family
they can snack on them because it's not נגמרה מלאכתן nigmerah melachtan
even though it's in your חצר chatzer and חצר Chatzer, is like
being brought into the house. Nevertheless, not נגמרה מלאכתן nigmerah melachtan it
can be snacked on.
You're in the מוקצה muktzah in the חצר.
chatzer Exactly. ותניא עלה, vetanya alah, we taught on it: רבי יעקב
מחייב. Rabbi Yaakov mechayeiv. רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov says, no, once it's
brought to the חצר chatzer, that's קובע. koveia. Okay, and רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan is now saying we don't פוסקן pasken that way. So
we have one idea that שבת is קובע. That's what we spent
all of yesterday or whatever and some of today discussing where we
tried to say that it was implicit in the משנה, Mishna. it's
רבי אליעזר, it's רבי יהושע, it's הלל. Hillel. But we reject that.
שבת is not קובע if it's not נגמרה מלאכתן. nigmerah melachtan. חצר
also not קובע even though רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov says it was
but that's the ברייתא Baraisa we talked the beginning of yesterday, that
חצר is not קובע if it's not
נגמרה מלאכתן. nigmerah melachtan. Okay, now, רבי יעקב מחייב Rabbi Yaakov mechayeiv
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
פוטר. Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda poter. תרומה, trumah, how about
תרומה? trumah? We talked before... ר' אליעזר אוסר לאכול מהן עראי וחכמים
מתירין. Rabbi Eliezer oser lachol mehen arai v'Chachamim matirin.
ר' אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says the act of תרומה Teruma has now
changed their status. They're now considered to be done and therefore you
can't snack from them and the חכמים Chachamim still allow it. So
we reject ר' אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer by תרומה, Teruma, we reject ר'
יעקב Rabbi Yaakov by חצר, we reject הלל Hillel and as we've
saw maybe also ר' אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and ר' יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
by שבת. None of these things change its status once before its
גמר מלאכה. gemar melacha. מקח, Mekach, purchase, דתניא detanya like we taught
in a ברייתא, braisa, even you might think sale selling it makes
it considered like different and changes its identity. No. הלוקח תאנים, Halokeach
te'einim, if you buy figs, again all this stuff for figs. Presumably
figs is cause figs is more flexible in terms of when you're
going to be done with it, whether you're planning on drying it
out or not as opposed to something like grapes or olives which
primarily are going to be made
into wine or oil.
But they constantly ripen on the tree over long period of
time, a fig,
the גמרא Gemara, says
that, that's
usually these are white ones, anyway, but okay. Yeah.
Okay. פירות, Peiros, where were we. הלוקח תאנים מעם הארץ. Halokeach te'einim
me'am ha'aretz.
So you're buying it from some person from the non-rabbinic class. Now
במקום שרוב בני אדם דורסים, bemakom she'rov bnei adam dorsim, in a
place where most people trample on it means which process it and
make it into these balls of figs and don't eat them fresh.
So here is a very interesting question. Normally when you buy something
from an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, its status is דמאי. demai. It
might have had תרומות ומעשרות Terumos uMaaseros. taken from it and therefore
the גמרא Gemara. says the majority of times we actually assume תרומות
ומעשרות Terumos uMaaseros were taken from it. But there's a minority of
times not and therefore you're obligated rabbinically to take תרומות ומעשרות. Terumos
uMaaseros That's דמאי. demai. Let's say I purchase it from the עם
הארץ am ha'aretz at a stage where for most people it's not
done being processed. Now am I obligated to take תרומות ומעשרות Terumos
uMaaseros ודאי vaday or דמאי? demai? Should I assume it definitely hasn't
had תרומות ומעשרות Terumos uMaaseros, taken because it's not even done in
the processing? So maybe even though it's much more likely he hasn't
taken תרומות ומעשרות Terumos uMaaseros maybe because it's not finished yet. So
maybe my obligation is a biblical obligation, it's a ודאי, vaday, maybe
I can't call it דמאי demai anymore because it's not yet at
a stage where I should assume he has taken it. So let's
take a look. I purchase this from an עם הארץ am ha'aretz
במקום שרוב בני אדם דורסים, bemakom she'rov bnei adam dorsim,
most people trample it and make it into these
balls, these rounds of figs and therefore this is not normally in
a finished state. אוכל מהן עראי, Ochel mehen arai, I can eat
from it עראי, arai, that would be true even if it was
definitely obligated. ומעשרן דמאי, Ume'asran demai,
and I take תרומות ומעשרות, Terumos uMaaseros I treat it like דמאי,
demai, not like ודאי. vaday. Why is that? Okay. So the גמרא
says שמע מינה תלת, shma mina tlas, you can hear from this
three things. שמע מינה מקח אינה קובעת, Shma mina mekach eina kova'at,
so the first thing, the thing that's really relevant for us is
the fact that I purchased it doesn't make it קבע. Because the
first teaching, forget the דמאי demai question, is that I can eat
from it snack from it. Now why? Because it's not נגמר מלאכתו,
because it hasn't finished being pressed. Okay, but one minute, a purchase
took place, maybe the act of sale, the act of purchase, defines
it now as a changed status and defines it as קבע. So
that's the first חידוש. chidush. No, even though you purchased it, since
it was not נגמר מלאכתו, you can still eat from it עראי.
arai. Number one. That's the first שמע מינה shma mina and that's
what's relevant for us. Now what are the other שמע מינה? shma
minas? ושמע מינה רוב עמי הארץ מעשרין הן, Vishma mina rov amei
ha'aretz me'asrin hen, okay, most עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz take מעשרות, maasros,
which is not a big חידוש, chidush, which means really just that
normally you're taking only דמאי demai when you buy from an עם
הארץ, am ha'aretz, it's a rabbinic, it's not a biblical obligated thing.
ושמע מינה Vishma mina the third one, which is the bigger חידוש
chidush is מעשרין דמאי מעם הארץ אפילו בדבר שלא נגמר מלאכה, me'asrin
demai me'am ha'aretz afilu bedavar shelo nigmar melacha, that you can take
דמאי demai from an עם הארץ am ha'aretz even when the מלאכה
melacha isn't finished being done. Now that's like really bizarre because if
most people don't take תרומות ומעשרות Terumos uMaaseros at this earlier stage
why isn't it a ודאי? vaday? So what you have to assume
is that while it is not yet done in the processing, still
it would be very common to take תרומות ומעשרות Terumos uMaaseros earlier
rather than later even though you're not yet obligated, even though you
know you can still be snacking on it. But that is clearly
the biggest חידוש. chidush. That here is something which number one it
starts off as a possibility that תרומות ומעשרות Terumos uMaaseros weren't taken
from it, right, because there's always some possibility when you buy from
an עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. Number two, it's earlier in the process.
So there's even a greater likelihood תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'maasros. weren't taken
from it and nevertheless we still say it's you know it's only
דמאי, demai, most of the time even at this stage probably תרומות
ומעשרות terumos u'maasros. were taken. To the huge חידוש. chidush. Okay, but
anyways, the part that's relevant for us is even after you've purchased
it you could still snack, so you see that's the idea that
מקח mekach is not קובע for תרומות ומעשרות. terumos u'maasros One minute.
So that's consistent with that ברייתא braisa that says מקח mekach is
not קובע for תרומות ומעשרות. ולאפוקי u'le'apukei and it rejects מהא דתנן
me'ha d't'nan the following משנה Mishna. that says מקח mekach is קובע.
What's that
משנה? המחליף פירות עם חבירו זה לאכול וזה לאכול. ha'machlif peiros im
chaveiro zeh le'echol v'zeh le'echol. We're going to swap fruits. I have
some grapes, I have some figs drying out, and you have some
grapes drying out. So I give you a bushel of you know
a basket of my drying out grapes for your basket of drying
out figs. Okay, I'm sorry, no, they're not drying out. I have
my fresh grapes, you have your fresh figs, so we're going to
swap we're going to swap baskets. Or זה לקצות וזה לקצות. zeh
le'katzos v'zeh le'katzos. They're drying out grapes and drying out figs and
we're going to swap baskets. The purpose of זה לקצות zeh le'katzos
is that it is לא נגמרה מלאכתו. lo nigmerah melachto. Okay. זה
לאכול וזה לקצות, zeh le'echol v'zeh le'katzos, or I give you grapes
to eat now and you give me figs to dry out. Doesn't
matter, in all those cases חייב. chayav. Because we swapped, that's a
type of a purchase, right? I sold you my grapes for your
figs, you sold me your figs for my grapes. And therefore even
though some of them are still in the process of drying out,
you cannot snack from them. Once they've been swapped it's like they've
been sold and even though לא נגמרה מלאכתו, lo nigmerah melachto, you
can't snack from it. So this ברייתא braisa assumes מקח mekach is
קובע. The teaching of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan rejects this ברייתא. braisa.
Okay, רבי יהודה אומר לאכול חייב ולקצות פטור. Rabbi Yehuda omer le'echol
chayav u'le'katzos patur. No, for eating you're חייב, chayav, if it's still
for drying out the act of swapping them, of selling them, does
not is not is not קובע and you could still snack from
them. So and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is ruling like רבי יעקב.
Rabbi Yaakov. So in the end we began the סוגיא by saying
a חצר is not קובע for something that's לא נגמרה מלאכתו. lo
nigmerah melachto. We wanted to know about שבת. We went through a
whole long convoluted discussion about our משנה because our משנה sounds like
שבת was קובע. We said well, maybe according to רבי אליעזר, maybe
otherwise it's according to חכמים Chachamim it's just דיבור. dibbur. Then we
saw that there was a רבי אליעזר and a רבי יהושע that
said that שבת was קובע and הלל Hillel that said שבת was
קובע. But then we ended by saying basically nothing is קובע. Before
the food is actually at the stage of גמר מלאכה, any other
things you do to it will not will still it's still not
done and therefore you can still snack from it, whether it's שבת,
whether it's bringing it into your חצר, whether it's selling it, whether
it's taking תרומה. terumah. None of those things change the physical reality
that the fruit are still in the process of are incomplete and
therefore they can still be snacked from. Okay, did you have a
question before?
Yes, I've never thought of this before. Is the word דמאי demai
etymologically an Aramaic question like "what is it"?
Oh, I don't know, that's a cute question. Sort of like מן.
man.
Yeah, that's what I was thinking. מן הוא. man hu. Is that
is that what's that's?
Interesting, I don't know what the etymology is, I don't know, you
could check Jastrow or the other dictionaries, I don't know. I see.
Okay. Alright. Alright, so הדרן עלך המביא. Hadran Alach Hamavi. So that
was a challenging end to that פרק, perek, which most of it
was about יום טוב, Yom Tov, but we had a little introduction
to תרומות ומעשרות and this basic idea of גמר מלאכה. We get
back to יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay, so a lot of the
last פרק, perek, you know, the last פרק perek was a lot
around fire issues, or a lot around making vessels, right, that even
though you can cook on יום טוב Yom Tov and so on
you can't make a vessel in the process of it. Most ראשונים
Rishonim assume that that's even according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that
allows מכשירי אוכל נפש. machshirei ochel nefesh. So that was sort of,
you know, a whole collection of things around making food and certain
limits of it and particularly in this in this area about like
new fire and other things particularly associating with making vessels. In this
פרק, perek, a lot of this פרק, perek, next פרק, perek, the
last פרק, perek, is going to be devoted to the question of
תחום. techum. Because even though carrying is allowed on יום טוב, Yom
Tov, תחום techum is not allowed and תחום techum can create certain
restrictions on food. Okay, normally we talk about תחום, techum, you know,
when we talked about תחום techum in עירובין Eruvin by שבת, it
was about like how far can you walk. That was the basic
question. Can I walk this far? But here the question is going
to be that תחום techum also impacts your food and your food
is limited by your תחום. techum. And can I use somebody else's
food to make, you know, food, you know, meals for me on
יום טוב Yom Tov if there's some difference in our תחומין techumin
and so on and we'll see all of those cases. Okay, but
so that's the way sort of the תחום techum question is going
to intersect with specifically all these food-related issues on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. We start though with a different point. We start with more
of this general issue of טרחא. tircha. Let's take a look.
משילין פירות דרך ארובה ביום טוב. Mashilin peiros derech arubbah b'Yom Tov.
You can lower down, we'll see what the word משילין mashilin means
in a minute, fruit through you've got your stuff again drying out
on the rooftop. Maybe you got up to the rooftop on ערב
יום טוב erev Yom Tov and said מכאן ועד כאן אני אוכל
mikan v'ad kan ani ochel like the previous משנה. Maybe it had
finished drying out so there's no מוקצה muktzah problem. Fine, there's no
מוקצה muktzah problem, now you want to get it into your house.
So what you can do is you can lower it through the
skylight, okay, on יום טוב. Yom Tov. אבל לא בשבת. Aval lo
b'Shabbos. Not on שבת. Now what's the חידוש chidush that you can
lower it? רש"י Rashi says, and the point is through your skylight,
but you can't basically take it down to the ground and then
bring it in your front door. Why? So that's going to be
a problem of, again, this issue of טרחא יתירה. tircha yeteira. It's
one thing to just throw it down the skylight, it's another thing
to be שלעפינג schlepping it down the ladder and bringing it in.
Again, we should always ask like these issues that, you know, the
גמרא does have on, you know, it's like a recurring theme, is
it a טרחא tircha issue or is it an עובדא דחול uvda
dechol issue? I would more say it's like an עובדא דחול, uvda
dechol, like hauling baskets of fruit down from the ladder off of
your rooftop bringing in the house, you know, that sort of evokes
that sense of like the working that you do, the, you know,
during the weekday, whereas just getting something into your house by throwing
it down the, the, the skylight
certainly is a שינוי. shinui. All right, and certainly is not, you
know, doesn't evoke this idea of like working. But okay, so that's
what it says, you can lower it down through the rooftops, but
not on שבת, so we'll have to see what makes שבת different.
ומכסין פירות בכלים מפני הדלף, Umechassin peirot bekeilim mipnei hadelef, you can
cover up if you've got fruit out in the yard, you know,
your, your baskets filled with apples and it's starting to rain, דלף
delef means a drip, you can go out and cover them over.
Okay, and again, that's not a concern of too much effort or
it's not a concern of עובדא דחול, uvda dechol, you're just trying
to protect, you know, you're, you're trying to protect your fruit, your
apples. וכן Vechen maybe it makes more sense to think if it
was wheat, something that'll get spoiled more by the rain. וכן כדי
יין וכדי שמן, Vechen kadei yayin vekadei shemen, if you've got, if
you've got pitchers of wine or oil and now they're, it's raining
into them, you can go out and cover them up. נותנין כלי
תחת הדלף בשבת, Notnin kli tachat hadelef beShabbat, and now this is
really a, by the way, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi adds to the end
of this so that it parallels, אבל לא בשבת. aval lo beShabbat.
You can do this on יום טוב Yom Tov to cover it
up and not on שבת, the same way you can lower the
fruit down the roof, the covering up from the rain. Okay, and
then the last line is נותנין כלי תחת הדלף בשבת, Notnin kli
tachat hadelef beShabbat, but you can actually put, so although some of
those things you couldn't do by שבת, if you, if there's a
hole in your roof, you can put a, you know, a pot
underneath the hole in order to catch the dripping rain, that you're
allowed to do even on שבת, that actually is taught in מסכת
שבת Masechet Shabbat as well.
So you don't actually want the water then, how can you do
that? What?
Let's say you just want... All right, well, let's not get into
that. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא.
Don't take why you're doing it. Okay, so, I know, I know.
So anyway, so רש"י Rashi by the way again says that all
these things are a טרחא tircha problem, right? You could have said
it's an עובדא דחול, uvda dechol, רש"י Rashi says it's a טרחא
tircha problem. רש"י Rashi also says that the reason we allowed, and
he's, he's invoking the later גמרא, is not that fundamentally it's not
an issue, maybe there would be some problems here of טרחא tircha
or of עובדא דחול, uvda dechol, but we're going to give you
a little bit more latitude to help you protect your things from
getting ruined. So that's הפסד ממון. hefsed mamon. So if you take
a look like at the middle רש"י Rashi here, like 10 lines
down from where the משנה begins, מכסין את הפירות, Mechassin et hapeirot,
he says ולא מן הטרחא שלא לצורך יום טוב הוא ששרו ליה
רבנן משום הפסד ממון Velo min hatircha shelo letzorech Yom Tov hu
shesharo lei Rabbanan mishum hefsed mamon because of הפסד. hefsed. Now, I
do want to say something about the word שלא לצורך יום טוב.
shelo letzorech Yom Tov. Is the טרחא tircha here concern just the
amount of effort it requires? How much effort does it require to,
you know, cover up some pitcher? I guess it matters how many
pitchers I have. But maybe the concern is not just how much
effort it requires, but whether I'm doing it לצורך יום טוב letzorech
Yom Tov or לצורך letzorech today. Okay, let me give you an
example, right? There's a fascinating question that comes up in general by
questions of הכנה. hachana. Okay, so here it is, I'm, I have
some cereal there for סעודה שלישית, Seudah Shlishit, okay, מילכיג milchig because
it's a long שבת now, and I took my milk out and
it's like half hour before שקיעה, shkiah, whatever it is. Can I
go ahead and put the milk back in the fridge? You say,
"No, you know, I mean, why you want to put the milk
back in the fridge? Because you don't want it to spoil." "Well,
that's because you want to have it for the weekday, so you're
doing הכנה hachana for the weekday." So you want to clean up?
No. So okay, if you just want to clean up, you don't
want the house to look messy, fine. But let's say no, you
really do want to put it in the fridge because you don't
want it to spoil. Okay? So
there are some people that say that. To me, I don't think
that, you're not doing it because you want it for the weekday,
you're doing it because you don't want it to get ruined. I
mean, this is something you spent money on, you don't want it
to go to waste. So I don't think that that's just because
in the reality is you're going to use it in the weekday.
It's not like you're preparing for the weekday, you're protecting your property.
You're allowed to go so... Right, so it's not exactly הכנה, hachana,
but it is interesting that רש"י Rashi says that the problem here
is טרחא לצורך חול. tircha letzorech chol. Is the problem that it's
טרחא tircha or is it... now the לצורך חול letzorech chol doesn't
mean that it's an איסור issur הכנה, hachana, but what he might
mean is you don't have the general allowance of אוכל נפש. ochel
nefesh. It's not like we're saying it's a problem because it's הכנה,
hachana, but what we are saying is, but it's still not something
that you're doing for benefiting today. If you're actually going to benefit
from it today, then that's the big אוכל נפש ochel nefesh מתיר.
matir. But you're not going to benefit from it today. So okay,
we understand you're protecting your investment, nobody's claiming a הכנה, hachana, but
it's not אוכל נפש ochel nefesh either. And therefore, are you allowed
to do it or not? How much latitude will we give you
to protect your property? And he says we will because of הפסד
ממון. hefsed mamon. Okay, let's take a look now at, at the
גמרא. איתמר. itmar.
But wait, sorry, that's just on יום טוב? Yom Tov?
That's on יום טוב, Yom Tov, אבל לא בשבת. aval lo beShabbat.
Okay, איתמר, itmar, oh my god, I didn't realize the time, but
we'll, the next 20 lines will be very fast. Rav Yehuda, oh
יפה. yofe. רב יהודה ורב נתן. Rav Yehuda veRav Natan. חד תני
משילין, chad tani mashilin, one says the verb in the משנה, his
text was משילין, mashilin, which means to lower, וחד תני משחילין, vechad
tani mashchilin, both of these are different ways of saying to lower.
אמר מר זוטרא, Amar Mar Zutra, מאן דתני משילין לא משתבש ומאן
דתני משחילין לא משתבש. man detani mashilin lo mishtabash uman detani mashchilin
lo mishtabash. If you have the one version or the other, it's
not necessarily a corruption, it's not necessarily a bad text. מאן דתני
משילין לא משתבש, man detani mashilin lo mishtabash, משילין mashilin is not
a bad text, דכתיב כי ישל זיתך, dechtiv ki yashal zeitecha, your
olive trees will drop their fruit. So משילין mashilin could mean to
drop fruit or to lower down the skylight. ומאן דתני משחילין לא
משתבש, uman detani mashchilin lo mishtabash, משחילין mashchilin also is a good
text because
we have השחול והכסול. hashchul vehakasul. These are two types of מומים
mumim in an animal, in a בכור, bechor, שחול shchul and a
כסול. kasul. What are these?
שחול שנשמטה ירכו, shchul shenishmeta yarecho, the שחול shchul means that the
thigh has been like, you know,
dislocated, thank you, וכסול שאחד מירכותיו גבוה מחברתה, vekasul she-echad miyarechotav gavoah
mechaverta,
that one of the thighs is higher than the other one, it's
located on the like in the back of the animal at a,
you know, they're not parallel, it's at a high location,
dislocated in a different way.
Well, yeah, but that actually more anatomically is in a different location.
Okay, now anyway, so שחול shchul means to be dislocated, to move,
to be removed in a way, and therefore it would also be
a proper
verb. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, מאן
דתני משילין לא משתבש ומאן דתני משחילין לא משתבש ומאן דתני מנשירין
לא משתבש. man detani mashilin lo mishtabash uman detani mashchilin lo mishtabash
uman detani menashirin lo mishtabash. So רש"י Rashi says nobody has claimed
that this is their text, but since he says there are four
three other words that look just like משילין mashilin and משחילין mashchilin
that also could just as legitimately be the right word in the
משנה. Okay, even though רש"י Rashi says nobody actually ever claimed to
have that text. מאן דתני משירין לא משתבש, man detani mashirin lo
mishtabash, the verb could be משירין, mashirin, דתנן רבי ישמעאל אומר נזיר
לא יחוף ראשו באדמה, detnan Rabbi Yishmael omer nazir lo yachof rosho
baadamah, a נזיר nazir cannot, you know, sort of launder his hair
or whatever, you know, shampoo his hair with like dirt or whatever
to scrub it, I'm not sure, whatever. Anyway, מפני שמשיר את השיער,
mipne shemeshir et hase-ar, because it causes the hair to drop and
you can't cut his hair. So the word משיר meshir means to
cause to fall off. So
משירין mashirin could be a good version. ומאן דתני משחירין לא משתבש,
uman detani mashchirin lo mishtabash, דתנן השחור והזוג של ספרים, detnan hashchor
vehazug shel saparim, that these are two types of scissors, like a
large scissor תוספות Tosafot says and a tiny little like a tiny
scissors, you know they sometimes the barbers have these little
clippers, ספרים, saparim, I'm sorry, ספרים, saparim, of a barber, so these
scissors of a barber, אף על פי שנחלקו טמאים, af al pi
shenechloku teme-im, even though the two halves, like the two blades, are
separate, they remain considered to be vessels. The point being that שחור,
shachor, why is a barber scissor called a שחור? shachor? Because it
cuts the hair. So משחירין mashchirin could have been a somehow the
word שחור shachor could mean to cut or to cause to fall
off, so that also could be a good version of our משנה.
And finally, ומאן דתני
מנשירין לא משתבש, uman detani menashirin lo mishtabash, and if you have
the word מנשירין, menashirin, so also that could mean to cause to
drop off, דתנן מי שנשרו כליו במים, detnan mi shenashru kelav bamayim,
if your clothes fell into water, מהלך בהם ואינו חושש, mehalech bahem
ve-eino choshesh, you can wear them on שבת even though you'll be
dripping wet, people won't think you did laundry on שבת, they'll understand
that your clothes fell into water, obviously you wouldn't be walking around
with dripping
clothes. אינמי ממה דתנן איזו לקט הנושר בשעת קצירה, inami mima detnan
eizu leket hanosher besha-at ketzirah, grain that drops בשעת קצירה. besha-at ketzirah.
So the word מנשירין menashirin and you might remember at the very
beginning of our מסכת, masechet, we talked about גזירה משום פירות הנושרין,
gezeirah mishum peirot hanoshrin, right, fruit that falls down. So there are
about five different verbs that this word could be, that all look
the same, that all roughly would mean to fall off. We will
continue with the הלכה halacha discussion of all of this tomorrow.